Finding Aid for Richard A. Laing papers, 1953-2000
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Richard A. Laing papers 1953-2000
Laing, Richard A.
3 linear feet
07100 Aa 2
Richard A. Laing was a researcher at the University of Michigan in the Logic of Computers Group. The Laing collection contains correspondence, publications, teaching materials, and research notes from Laing's investigations into biological modeling, automata theory, and artificial intelligence.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was donated in February 2007 by Ellen Johnston Laing (donor no. 9850 ).
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Richard A. Laing was born on March 20, 1927 in New York, NY. He received his B.A. and M.A. degrees from the University of Michigan in 1950 and 1953 respectively, and his PhD from SUNY Binghamton in 1977. He was a researcher with the University of Michigan, working as a Research Assistant with the Willow Run Laboratories from 1954-1957, and in various research capacities with the Logic of Computers Group (LoCG). His involvement with the LoCG was his primary professional activity at the University of Michigan.
The Logic of Computers Group at the University of Michigan was established in 1956 as an informal group of faculty members from various departments who were interested in studying the logical formalisms related to computers and natural systems. The group was directed by philosophy professor Arthur Burks and early on worked out of the Operations Research Department of the Engineering Research Institute. In 1957, Burks and Gordon Peterson, of the Phonetics Laboratory in the Department of Speech, petitioned the graduate school, and along with five other professors were constituted a committee with power to award advanced graduate degrees in "Communications Sciences." The program was chaired by Peterson until it achieved departmental status in 1965. After a year under an interim chairman, Burks chaired the "Computer and Communications Sciences" Department until 1971. The LoCG was an important component of both the early program and, later, the department. Although it worked out of its own computing center and was funded entirely by grants from governmental agencies, it provided the department with faculty expertise and produced a large percentage of the departmental PhDs.
Apart from his involvement at the University of Michigan, Laing was also a participant in other research ventures, including the NASA Summer Study for the Advanced Automation for Space Missions in 1980, and the University of Oregon Machines and Behavior program in 1981. He was also a professor of Literature at Ching Yi College in Taichung, Taiwan, in 1964.
Laing's scientific research interests centered around the interplay of computers and biological systems. His technical writings dealt with the sociological aspects of computer mechanization, as well as the principles of artificial intelligence, automata and computability theory and biological modeling.
Laing published extensively in a variety of scholarly journals in the biological and computer sciences, including the Journal of Cybernetics, the Journal of Theoretical Biology, and Synthese. Apart from his scholarly writing, Laing was also an avid author of fiction, and winner of the University of Michigan Hopwood Award for Creative Writing in 1953.
The Richard A. Laing papers contain correspondence, publications, teaching materials, and research notes from Laing's investigations into biological modeling, automata theory, and artificial intelligence. The papers are divided into five main series which document his professional career: Articles, Biographical Materials, Correspondence, Research, and Teaching.
Subjects:
Laing, Richard A.; Artificial intelligence.; Computers--Study and teaching.; Computer science.; Machine theory.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan. Logic of Computers Group.
- Articles
  Articles contains a chronologically organized series of Laing's published articles beginning in 1961 and ending in 1987. The articles in this series are reprints provided by publishers. They do not represent a comprehensive run of Laing's published materials. In addition to his articles, the series also contains an index to the publications of the Logic of Computers Group.
  - Undated (Box 1)
    - Automata Theory and Development, II Morphogenesis of Simple Artificial Organisms circa 1972 (Box 1)
  - 1961-1967
    - Book Review: Mortimer Taube, Computers and Common Sense 1961 (Box 1)
    - Technical Report: "Commutative Machines" with Jesse B. Wright 1962 (Box 1)
    - Technical Report: "Tape Machine Realizations of Commutative-Regular Events," 1965 (Box 1)
    - Technical Report: "Realization and Complexity of Commutative Events," 1967 (Box 1)
  - 1969-1970
    - Technical Report: "Formalisms for Living Systems (Part I)," 1969 (Box 1)
    - Technical Report: "Asexual and Sexual Reproduction Expressed in the Von Neumann Cellular System (Formalisms for Living Systems (Part I) Sections 9.2, 9.3, and 9.4) 1970 (Box 1)
    - "A Cell Space Embedding of Simulated Living Cells" with E.D. Goodman and R. Weinberg Bio-Medical Computing, Vol. 2, 1971 (Box 1)
    - "Formalisms for Biology: A Hierarchy of Developmental Processes," International Journal of Neuroscience, Vol. 2, 1971 (Box 1)
  - 1971-1987
    - "Computer Simulation of a Living Cell: Metabolic Control System Experiments," with Roger Weinberg and Bernard Zeigler, Journal of Cybernetics, Vol. 1, No. 2, 1971 (Box 1)
    - "Artificial Organisms and Autonomous Cell Rules," Journal of Cybernetics, Vol. 2, No. 1, 1972 (Box 1)
    - "The Capabilities of Some Species of Artificial Organisms," Journal of Cybernetics, Vol. 3, No. 2, 1973 (Box 1)
    - "A Note on Maxwell's Demon and Universal Computation," Journal of Cybernetics, Vol. 3, No. 2, 1973 (Box 1)
    - "Maxwell's Demon and Computation," Philosophy of Science, Vol. 41, No. 2, 1974 (Box 1)
    - "Artificial Molecular Machines: A Rapprochement Between Kinematic and Tessellation Automata," Proceedings of the International Symposium on Uniformly Structured Automata and Logic, 1975 (Box 1)
    - Technical Report: "Computation, Self-Description, Construction, and Reproduction in Some Artificial Molecular Machine Systems," Logic of Computers Group 1975 (Box 1)
    - "Automaton Introspection," Journal of Computer and System Sciences, Vol. 13, No. 2, 1976 (Box 1)
    - "Automaton Models of Reproduction by Self-inspection," Journal of Theoretical Biology, Vol. 66, 1977 (Box 1)
    - "Anomalies of Self-Description," Synthesis, Vol. 38, 1978 (Box 1)
    - "Machines as Organisms: An Exploration of the Relevance of Recent Results," BioSystems, Vol. 11, 1979 (Box 1)
    - Lecture: "Machine Replication" (Recorded and Prepared by Robert A. Freitas Jr.," 1980 (Box 1)
    - "Self-Replication," Encyclopedia of Artificial Intelligence, 1987 (Box 1)
    - "Advanced Automation for Space Missions" 1980 (Box 1)
      (In NASA Conference Publication 2255)
  - Logic of Computers Index (Box 1)
  - Novel: Jade Ecstasy, by Celia Gardner Richards (pen name) (Box 1)
- Biographical Materials
  Biographical Materials contains Laing's resumes listing his professional involvements through the early 1980s.
  - Resumes (Box 1)
- Correspondence
  Correspondence contains letters to and from Laing at various stages in his career. The arrangement of this correspondence reflects Laing's own organizational system. In the A-Z folders are letters which Laing kept in a large according filing system, arranged alphabetically. All other correspondence is arranged by subject or correspondent. This series also contains a collection of printed-out emails, organized separately by Laing. The University folder contains correspondence culled from various parts of the collection relating to the Laing's tenure at the University of Michigan.
  - A-Z, 20 folders (Box 1)
  - Burks Festschrift (Box 1)
  - Elliott, Charles (Box 1)
  - Email (Box 1)
  - Freitas, Robert (Box 1)
  - Minsky, Marvin (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
  - Multi-Tape (Box 1)
  - University (Box 1)
  - Von Tiesenhausen (Box 1)
- Research
  The Research series makes up the majority of the Laing papers and contains perhaps the most significant insight into his professional identity. Laing used various methods of note-taking, and a sampling of each of these systems is represented in the series. First, collections of short essays, generally no longer than two pages, were filed loose-leaf in folders. These essays are unpublished material, and range from unedited thoughts and reflections, to more polished responses to ideas in his field. Laing also kept materials which he labeled "Technical Notes". These were generally kept in binders and notebooks. The binders have been numbered by the archivist to facilitate research, as they are untitled and undated. Finally, a run of composition notebooks were numbered by Laing, either by date or according to a numbering system. The Research series also contains documentation of Laing's work at the Willow Run Laboratories during the mid-1950s.
  - Miscellaneous Notes, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Replicating Lunar Factory Study Group (Box 2)
  - Short Essays, 9 folders
  - Technical Notes
    - Binder #1, 3 folders (Box 2)
    - Binder #2 (Box 2)
    - Binder #3, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Binder #4, 4 folders (Box 2)
    - Binder #5 (Box 3)
    - Binder #6 (Box 3)
    - Notebook 1/24/1958 (Box 3)
    - Notebook 3/5/1958 (Box 3)
    - Notebook, A-1 (Box 3)
    - Notebook, B-1 (Box 3)
    - Notebook, B-2 (Box 3)
    - Notebook, B-3 (Box 3)
    - Notebook, B-4 (Box 3)
    - Notebook, B-5 (Box 3)
    - Notebook, B-6 (Box 3)
    - Notebook 8 (Box 3)
    - Notebook: "Godel's Incompleteness Theorem" (Box 3)
    - Some Reflections on Production Rules for Biological Systems, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Willow Run
    - Intelligence Output and the Intelligence Functions at Battalion Staff Level 1956 (Box 3)
    - Notes and Comments 1956 (Box 3)
    - Operation All-American 1953 (Box 3)
    - Operation Louise 1956 (Box 3)
    - Procedures in the Preparation and Conduct of Command Post Exercises (Box 3)
- Teaching
  The Teaching series contains materials Laing used for lectures in classes at the University of Michigan, including CCS 320, Computers and Society, as well as a lecture given at Los Alamos Laboratories.
  - CCS 200, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - CCS 320 (Box 3)
  - Los Alamos Lecture (Box 3)